Today's דף daf is י"ז Yud Zayin and we pick up at
the two lines at the bottom of ט"ז עמוד ב. Tet Zayin
Amud Bet. We're dealing with the different types of practices that they
would do at first weddings in order to serve as evidence whether,
when the couple gets divorced 20 years later, had it been was
it a first wedding or not, how much the כתובה ketubah was.
So in that context we were talking about different types of practices,
whole fascinating little thing with a barrel of wine, the barrel of
wine emerging again around the whole discussions of sort of metaphors and
images about virginity. Anyway, so with that we transition to a famous
debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, two
lines from the bottom ט"ז עמוד ב. Tet Zayin Amud Bet.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Our rabbis taught: כיצד מרקדים לפני הכלה? Keitzad
merakdim lifnei hakallah? How does one dance before the
כלה? kallah? בית שמאי אומרים: Beit Shammai omrim: what does one say
when one dances before the כלה? kallah? בית שמאי אומרים: Beit Shammai
omrim: כלה כמות שהיא. Kallah kemoshechi. You praise her according to who
she is, what she is. So, you know, you lie on the
line, you know, you're brutally honest. Well, I don't know brutally, but
anyway. ובית הלל אומרים: U-Beit Hillel omrim: כלה נאה וחסודה. Kallah na'ah
vechasudah. No, you say that she's a beautiful and charming כלה. kallah.
So, אמרו להן בית שמאי לבית הלל, Amru lahen Beit Shammai le-Beit
Hillel, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai said to בית הלל: Beit Hillel:
הרי שהייתה חיגרת או סומא, Harei shehayetah chigeret o sumah, let's say
that she was lame or blind. Fascinating that they hone in specifically
on physical disabilities. אומרים
לה כלה נאה וחסודה? Omrim lah kallah na'ah vechasudah? Would you say
beautiful and charming? והתורה אמרה מדבר שקר תרחק. Ve-hatorah amrah midvar sheker
tirchak. You should distance yourself from a matter of lie. אמרו להן
בית הלל לבית שמאי, Amru lahen Beit Hillel le-Beit Shammai, so בית
הלל Beit Hillel said to בית שמאי: Beit Shammai: לדבריכם, Lidvreichem, and
according to you, מי שלקח מקח רע מן השוק, Mi shelakach mikach
ra min hashuk, if somebody purchased something bad, made a bad purchasing
purchase decision from the שוק, shuk, from the marketplace, somebody comes and
says to you, what do you think of my new hat? ישבחנו
בעיניו או יגננו בעיניו? Yishabchenu be'einav o yiganenu be'einav? Do you say,
oh, it looks so charming, it looks so beautiful on you, or
do you say actually that's a pretty disgusting purchase? הוי אומר ישבחנו
בעיניו. Hevei omer yishabchenu be'einav. So says, so you obviously would say
ישבחנו בעיניו, yishabchenu be'einav, you should praise it.
מכאן אמרו חכמים. Mikan amru chachamim. So therefore from here the חכמים
chachamim said: לעולם תהא דעתו של אדם מעורבת עם הבריות. Le'olam tehei
da'ato shel adam me'urevet im habriyot. A person should always be, you
know, their, you know, find favor, do something that is desirable in
the eyes of people. So what does so first of all let's
just say a minute about that last line. I mean, obviously and
also just again note how, you know, I think disturbing it is
from our from where we stand that the assumption that somebody with
a physical disability is being put into this type automatically this type
of a category. I mean, you know, there are people that somebody
would say is not the type of person most people would want
to be married with, but the assumption to, but the assumption that
that you identify that as somebody with a physical disability and that's
what whatever anyway. All right, so that's number one. Number two is
that דעתו של אדם מעורבת עם הבריות. Da'ato shel adam me'urevet im
habriyot. רש"י Rashi says לעשות לאיש ואיש כרצונו. La'asot le-ish ve-ish kirtzono.
So you see that very much tying into a פורים Purim theme,
right?
לעשות
כדת איש ואיש. La'asot kidat ish va-ish.
Anyway,
so basically, which means that there's a type of here an idea
of I mean בית הלל Beit Hillel isn't sort of saying you
do it because like it's objectively true. You do it because of
your sensitivity to people and wanting to, you know, to do for
people what they want and not necessarily what's necessarily always sort of,
you know, sort of impose upon them some harsh objective truth. So
therefore, you know, from that person's perspective, you know, if somebody is
asked says what do you think about my new hat, they're asking
for a compliment. They don't want the truth. They want you to
say something nice. So you say something nice then that's what, you
know, and that's you should be focusing on sort of accommodating people
in their needs and not necessarily some sense of objective truth, which
you know, to some degree is how many people assume is the
fundamental debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
in most things, you know. I mean I think that a nice
distillation of it is the whole question about מה נברא תחילה, Mah
nivra techilah, שמים או ארץ. Shamayim o aretz. That בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says שמים נברא תחילה Shamayim nivra techilah and בית הלל Beit
Hillel says ארץ נברא תחילה, Aretz nivra techilah, which basically means like
do you sort of see like, you know, sort of some objective
truth is where our focus is, and, you know, human beings have
to just, you know, have to accommodate themselves to the objective truth
whether they like it or not. Or do you say no, ארץ
נברא תחילה, Aretz nivra techilah, we start with human realities and human
concerns and those are their own sort of realities, whatever, and, and,
you know, and then we have to sort of figure out how
to make, you know, facts sort of, you know, work within that
context. So you know, a lot of that has to do with,
right, whether you're how much you're going to be a מחמיר machmir
or a מקיל meikel as well, how much are you sort of
seeing that you have a responsibility fundamentally to making things work for
human beings and accommodating human beings. So to the degree that
you can compare the כלה kallah to some
merchandise,
yeah, well that's clearly true. So, now number one, number two is,
right, in terms of this כלה כמות שהיא, kallah kemoshechi, first of
all, you know, as Michael said, try singing that to the music,
right? כלה כמות, Kallah kemot, no, it doesn't work anyway.
Anyway fine. So what did they say when they said כלה כמו
שהיא? kallah k'moshehee?
So רש"י Rashi says לפי יופיה וחשיבותה מקלסים אותה. l'phi yophya v'chashivuta
m'kalsim otah.
So you emphasize you know what is beautiful about her, what's great
about her. Of course that's very nice, but let's say there's nothing
nice to say, you know?
So, so you know how do you, so what do you do?
So take a look at תוספות. Tosfos. So תוספות Tosfos has כלה
כמו שהיא kallah k'moshehee ואם יש בה מום ישתקו ולא ישבחוה. v'im
yesh ba mum yishtaku v'lo yishabchuha.
Okay, and if she's nothing nice to say so as my mom
always used to tell me, if you have nothing nice to say
don't say anything at all. Okay, או אינמי o inami or ישבחו
בדבר נאה שיש בה yishabchu b'davar na'eh sheyesh ba כגון בעינה או
בידיה. k'gon b'eina o b'yada.
So you point out, oh you know she's got such a good
sense of humor, she's whatever. You say, you find something nice to
say. אם הן יפות im hen yafot ובית הלל אומרים ישבחו לגמרי.
u'Beis Hillel omrim yishabchu l'gamri.
No, you have to just generally say כלה נאה וחסודה kallah na'ah
v'chasudah כשמזכירין מה שיש בה לשבח k'shemaskirin mah sheyesh ba l'shevach מכלל
דשאר לגנאי. mi'chlal d'sha'ar li'gnai.
Right,
everybody else you say how beautiful they are and this one you
say she's got a good sense of humor, so okay people read
between the lines.
So and then it says, and so
okay so that's so there so so number one so תוספות Tosfos
reads by the way that כלה כמו שהיא kallah k'moshehee means literally
you find something nice to say. So you know you also understand
where בית הלל Beis Hillel is saying the formulaic type of a
thing, כלה נאה וחסודה, kallah na'ah v'chasudah, it's not totally שקר, sheker,
right? It's like formulaic, okay, so כלה נאה וחסודה kallah na'ah v'chasudah
could be interpreted to mean first of all the fact that it's
formulaic means that everybody understands that it's
formulaic so nobody is reading it literally number one and number two
is also that it could mean you know every obviously you know
that she's beautiful in the eyes of the beholder that for you
know so if you say it like that you know and you
say it generically it means you know for everybody you know for
everyone there you know there's a subjective reality to that. המהרש"א The
Maharsha says that he tries to say that that's בית שמאי Beis
Shammai would say the same thing. בית שמאי Beis Shammai is not
being so harsh that when בית שמאי Beis Shammai says כלה כמו
שהיא kallah k'moshehee it does not mean
that at every wedding you decide what to say. You say oh
for this one you're going to say this and this one you're
going to say that. It means that you say how
this כלה kallah however she is, she's beautiful for her husband. So
you know it's sort of a type of like a formulaic statement.
Her husband finds her beautiful. Okay, so then the only difference is
that בית שמאי Beis Shammai if that's being read is underscoring this
fact that they're making a subjective statement whereas בית הלל Beis Hillel
is not underscoring it. Anyway but that's a way המהרש"א the Maharsha
tries to tone down a little bit the בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
And let's just look at this next תוספות: Tosfos: ישבחנה בעיניו או
יגננה בעיניו yishabchenu b'einav o y'ganenu b'einav ובית שמאי סברי u'Beis Shammai
savri אף על גב דישבחנה בעיניו. af al gav d'yishabchenu b'einav.
Of course you're supposed to say something nice to a person when
they say what do you think about my new hat? אין להם
לחכמים לתקן ein lahem l'chachamim l'saken ויזקקו לומר שקר v'yizakku l'mar sheker
התורה אמרה מדבר שקר תרחק. ha'Torah amrah mi'devar sheker tirchak.
So תוספות Tosfos interestingly he also tones down בית שמאי Beis Shammai
a little bit. Somebody comes to you and says what do you
think about my new hat? בית שמאי Beis Shammai is not supposed
to say you're supposed to say well I like your tie
or say actually I think it's ugly. No there they admit that
there's an idea of like a white lie and maybe or saying
something generic and you know being sensitive to how people you know
what people want to hear. But they just think that's not going
to mean that we're going to instantiate that in a rabbinic תקנה.
takkanah. Okay, so that's a couple ways of toning down בית שמאי
Beis Shammai a little bit, yeah.
So as I was thinking is it's just very interesting the dynamic
is according to the way רש"י Rashi was saying it you praise
her for what it's worth, right? So then I don't know why
you know if that's really true then בית שמאי Beis Shammai would
say כגון סומא k'gon suma you know כלה נאה וחסודה kallah na'ah
v'chasudah and
also like בית הלל's Beis Hillel response, right? ישבחנה או יגננה yishabchenu
o y'ganenu doesn't mean that בית שמאי Beis Shammai think יגננה, y'ganenu,
right? בית שמאי Beis Shammai would still say...
Yeah
but that's exactly תוספות's Tosfos point if you feel you're not going
to have anything nice to say you're not going to say anything
so that's going to be an implicit critique, you know?
But you find something else to say, oh she's like so...
Alright, you're already reading תוספות Tosfos into it and the problem is
again that when you sort of say certain things and you're not
saying other things there's an implicit statement being made.
You're saying something different for everybody else. For everybody.
Alright, what can I say, yes.
He says something about the פסוק. pasuk.
Well yeah, thank you, that's also true. Meaning again this is all
about from the man's perspective and as you know David pointed out
it's all about if somebody buys a purchase, what do you say?
Right, the man is the one who is taking a wife, he's
the one purchasing her, she's the commodity and has did he make
a good purchase or not a good purchase, right?
And maybe he's marrying up, maybe you know.
Yeah I know that could be as a social reality but again
you know that's not primarily the framework that this is all being
looked at.
It's interesting I kind of imagine why this is in the context
of ריקוד, rikud, right, what kind
of ריקוד.
rikud. That's a good point, you're right.
I mean we dance to the song,
yeah.
So what's the question?
No כיצד מרקדין לפני הכלה. Keitzad m'rakdin l'pne ha'kallah. Now clearly they
would do you know they would say things as they would do
the ריקוד rikud but you're right, yeah. Okay, yeah, right. Well we're
actually going to look in
a
minute. this got, it lets in this ray of light. I'm going
to try to do something. I know.
Let's see like the blinds maybe if that's going to make, I
don't know if that does, I don't know if that does anything.
All right. Anyway, moving on. Not doing anything.
All right. Yeah. Okay fine, moving on. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata
Rav Dimi amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came he said the
following: הכי שרו קמי כלתא במערבא. Hachi sharu kamei kallah b'Ma'arava.
This is what they sing in front of a bride in the
west, in ארץ ישראל: Eretz Yisrael: לא כחל ולא שרק ולא פירכוס
ויעלת חן. Lo kchal v'lo srak v'lo pirchus v'ya'alat chen.
No, yeah, it's very beautiful I think. Anyway, so you know, no
eyeshadow and no rouge and no hairdo and she still is very
beautiful or חן chen more like a charm. So meaning she has
an inner beauty, okay, or she has a natural beauty. You don't
need to sort of fancy it up and make her up, she's
got a very, she's got a natural beauty, which exactly
as the hairdresser and getting, yeah exactly. Well the מהרש"א Maharsha interestingly
tries to tie it into the בית הלל בית שמאי Beit Hillel
Beit Shammai issues as well, which is like you know sort of
maybe saying like you don't have to lavish her with false praise,
you know, somehow it's a natural beauty.
Is it more בית שמאי Beit Shammai way?
I don't know, I forget exactly how he ties it in. כי
סמכו רבנן לרבי זירא, Ki samchu rabbanan l'Rabbi Zeira, anyway, so
when the rabbis gave סמיכה smicha to רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, שרו
ליה הכי, sharu lei hachi, they sang the following. So this is
interesting. They had a whole singing, you know, חג הסמיכה, chag hasmicha,
they had, they did singing. That's a precedent for Chovevei that's been
doing that for many years, we have singing and dancing at our
חג הסמיכה. chag hasmicha. Okay we just don't sing כיצד מרקדין לפני
הכלה, Keitzad merakdin lifnei hakallah, but now they'll, now we'll get ideas.
So שרו ליה הכי, sharu lei hachi, this is how they used
to sing: לא כחל ולא שרק ולא פירכוס ויעלת חן. Lo kchal
v'lo srak v'lo pirchus v'ya'alat chen.
They sang the same thing. Without eyeshadow and rouge or hairdo and
still beautiful. So he has a true, like a natural beauty. I
don't get it, but okay.
What don't you get? What you don't get is the comparison.
It's the same song.
Well, I mean, there is something very beautiful about that as a
line. But I do think again what's fascinating and this obviously is
a, this obviously is a major theme is the comparing of, you
know, of rabbinic learning תורה Torah like, you know, I mean what's
his name, Daniel Boyarin has the whole thing of like תורה Torah
as the other woman, you know. So the whole relationship of the
תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham to תורה Torah is a very much of
a, of a man, of a, you know, a male-female
relationship but maybe sometimes even an erotic relationship. You know, husbands leaving
their wives in order to go learn תורה. Torah. So here this
guy, you know, is getting סמיכה, smicha, you know, maybe it's sort
of a sense of like marrying himself to the תורה. Torah. Whatever.
Of course he points out that he's the bride here. He's the
bride. He's not the man, you see, in the whole other, the
תורה Torah is the bride, but they're singing this about him. They're
singing about him what they would sing about the bride.
Maybe it's because of the תורה. Torah.
Oh maybe, I don't know. שרו ליה sharu lei and
they say קמי, kamei, well קמי כלתא kamei kallah and here it's,
maybe it's ליה, lei, it could be. Anyway, let me just see
what the מהרש"א Maharsha says about this לא כחל. lo kchal. He
says something nice about this.
No. Okay fine. All right. So anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
goes on and it says like this. כי סמכו רבנן לרבי אמי
ולרבי אסי, Ki samchu rabbanan l'Rabbi Ami u'l'Rabbi Assi,
when the rabbis gave סמיכה smicha to רבי אמי Rabbi Ami and
רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, שרו ליה הכי, sharu lei hachi, this is
what they sang in front of them or to them: כל מנדיין
וכל מנדיין סמוכו לנא, Kol mindein v'kol mindein s'muchu lana,
anybody like this one and this one we should give סמיכה smicha
from us. לא תסמכו לנא לא מן סרמיסין ולא מן סרמיטין, Lo
t'samchu lana, lo min sarmisin v'lo min sarmitin,
not from the סרמיסין sarmisin and not from the סרמיטין. sarmitin. Now
what were they? So רש"י Rashi says the סרמיסין sarmisin are the
people that basically like from the word לסרס, lesares, basically, yeah no
no no, that's not, no that's different, לסרס, lesares, twist, people that,
you know, twist the meaning of the תורה. Torah. וסרמיטין v'sarmitin רש"י
Rashi says לשון סמרטוטין, lashon samtutim, which I guess he means like
rags, you know, or something. Anyway, you know, give, we should get
סמיכה smicha in these people not from like the bad, not you
know not from people that are undeserving. Which is again, I'd rather
somebody sing before me that I have a natural beauty than like,
oh well, he's better than somebody who's a perverter of the תורה.
Torah. Exactly.
Okay. ואמרי לה, V'amri lah, I really don't get this whole thing.
ואמרי לה, V'amri lah, לא מן חמיסין ולא מן תרמיסין, lo min
chamisim v'lo min turmisim,
not from the חמיסין chamisim and the תרמיסין. turmisim. Who are the
חמיסין? chamisim? So רש"י Rashi says the word חמיסין chamisim is like
from the word חמשה, chamisha, which means people that only give a
fifth of the reasons, you know, or only learn a fifth of
a מסכת. masechet. And the תרמיסין turmisim רש"י Rashi says he doesn't
know exactly and then some parentheses say that some others sing like
empty people, worthless people, etc. Okay again it's a pretty funny type
of a שבח. shvach. At least you're not, at least you're not
like a corrupt know-nothing. All right anyway.
It's just like the coin that's a third of something.
Oh
I see. Oh. No nickels and dimes. The תורמוס Turmus wasn't that
a vegetable? The
תורמוס Turmus is a vegetable. I don't know anyway neither do I.
That's what the. Okay anyway רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, רבי אבהו Rabbi
Abbahu כי הוי אתי
ki
havah
atei
by the way there's an interesting line in the מהרש"א Maharsha on
this, I'll just read the one line, the מהרש"א Maharsha says כי
בעוונותינו רבים מהרבנים שנכשלים
בזה בדור הזה
ki ba-avonoteinu rabbim me-ha-rabbanim
she-nichshalim be-zeh ba-dor ha-zeh
to have like some of these bad character traits, וראוי הדבר לתקן
על פי חכמי הארצות והקצינים. ve-ra'uy ha-davar le-takken al pi chachmei ha-artzot
ve-ha-ktzinim.
I don't know what he's talking about but he's complaining about rabbinic
authority in his day that undeserving people and we need to get
the secular authorities involved to do something about it. So somebody should
go try to unpack that מהרש"א. Maharsha. Okay so that's maybe the
context of this. Finally we got a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Finally
we got somebody who's not like a corrupt person as a רבי.
rebbe. רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu כי הוי אתי ממתיבתא לבי קיסר ki
havah atei mi-metivta le-vei keisar
when רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu would go from the ישיבה yeshiva to
the house of the Caesar, נפקן אמהתא דבי קיסר
לאפיה nafkan amhata de-vei keisar le-apeih the maidservants of the house of
the Caesar would come out to greet him, ומשרין ליה הכי u-msharin
leih hachi and they'd sing to him, presumably he would be aglow
from the learning of תורה. Torah. And they'd sing to him the
following way: רבא דעמיה ומדברנא דאומתיה בוצינא דנהורא ברוך מתייך לשלום Rabba
de-ameih u-madbarna de-umteih botzina de-nehora baruch matyeich le-shalom teacher of his people,
master of his people and leader of his nation, the candle of
light,
blessed be your coming in peace. Okay so basically he would be
recognized even in the house of the Caesar and presumably it's about
leaving the ישיבה yeshiva so there'd be that sense of this glow
about him. So again what's fascinating and this comes as a major
theme is the whole issues about marriage automatically suggest again sort of
you see it all from the very male rabbinic perspective. First we
have the woman as purchase and then also the whole sort of
primary focus and enterprise on learning so the whole discussions of marriage
automatically wind up translating in terms of issues about relationship to the
תורה Torah and singing in somebody who's been learning תורה Torah and
so on. Okay. So אמרו עליו על רבי יהודה ברבי אלעאי Amru
alav al Rabbi Yehuda be-Rabbi Ilai they said about רבי יהודה ברבי
אלעאי Rabbi Yehuda be-Rabbi Ilai שהיה נוטל בד של הדס she-hayah motel
bad shel hadas he would take a branch of a myrtle ומרקד
לפני הכלה u-merakked lifnei ha-kallah and dance in front of the כלה.
kallah. So there's the מרקד merakked and now it's not just with
words but also with like shtick. Exactly. ואומר ve-omer and he would
say and here you go Dov, כלה נאה וחסודה. kallah na'ah ve-chasudah.
So there you go it actually he would do the same he
would sing as he would be doing it. ורב שמואל בר רב
יצחק מרקד אתלת. ve-Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak merakked a-tlat. And Rav
Shmuel
bar Rav Yitzchak would dance by three. Now what does by three
mean? So רש"י Rashi says it means he would juggle three types
of הדסים hadasim okay but the מהרש"א Maharsha says first of all
it wouldn't be אתלת a-tlat that would be בתלת bi-tlat and also
try juggling a branch of myrtle, you need
things
that are a little bit more dense.
What? Stood on three people?
Stood on three people. The מהרש"א Maharsha says it means he would
dance more he would dance more vigorously than three other people. Okay
so אמר רבי זירא Amar Rabbi Zeira קמחסיף לן סבא ka-machsif lan
sabba
the elder is embarrassing us. So according to the רש"י's Rashi read
the simple read he's embarrassing us because he's acting well that's what
the מהרש"א Maharsha says. רש"י Rashi says it just means he's embarrassing
us because he's like getting out of hand like it's not dignified.
The מהרש"א Maharsha says according to his read he's embarrassing us because
we're young people and he's dancing and he's dancing three times as
much as us. Okay כי נח נפשיה ki nach nafsheih when he
died, אפסיק עמודא דנורא בין דידיה לכולא עלמא afsik amuda de-nura bein
dideih le-chulei alma
a pillar of fire separated between him and everybody else. When they
were somehow taking him to be buried some pillar of fire came
and separated off his coffin from the rest of the people or
maybe when they brought him into the cave or when they buried
him. Okay וגמירי דלא אפסיק עמודא דנורא ve-gemiri de-la afsik amuda de-nura
a pillar of fire only interrupts אלא לחד בדרא אי לתרי בדרא
ella le-chad be-dara ei le-trei be-dara
only for a unique one or two people in the generation because
it basically is a way of symbolizing they're in a class by
themselves. They're separated off from all the rest of the people. So
basically here they were according to the simple read of the גמרא
Gemara embarrassed by how out of hand he got and wasn't dignified
and now we see that he was on a higher level, he
was like the אחד בדורו. echad be-doro. Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says as if we missed the point, so
אמר רבי זירא amar Rabbi Zeira the same רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
who said a minute ago that he's embarrassing us, now רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira said אהני ליה שוטיתא דסבא ahani leih shutita de-sabba the
שוטיתא shutita
which is רש"י Rashi says means the branch of the elder helped
him, so where were we, ואמרי לה שטותיה דסבא ve-amrei lah shtuteih
de-sabba
and some say the wildness like the שטות shtut of the
elder, ואמרי לה שיטתיה דסבא ve-amrei lah shitateih de-sabba
his approach. So one or the other helped him. Meaning it's because
of the way he was so much was so vigorous in his
dancing and he got out of hand or whatever, that was in
the end what made him so special and unique is that he
sort of was מוחל mochel on his own כבוד kavod in order
to bring שמחה simcha to the חתן. chatan. So it reminds you
of all those stories, right, of דוד המלך Dovid Hamelech and מיכל.
Michal. Was it מיכל? Michal? Right? Yeah, דוד המלך Dovid Hamelech and
מיכל. Michal.
Would the rabbis know that too?
I don't know, you know, well, but again, there's always that balance
between dignity and appropriateness. David was dancing before the ארון, Aron, he
was dancing in front of a כלה. kallah. Okay, but that is
interesting. By the way, although the גמרא Gemara is not making that
comparison, right, that is interesting in the reverse, right? What what in
the תורה Torah is about dancing in front of the ארון, Aron,
you know, and is that over is that inappropriate for your dignity?
Here it's being compared you know here there's a very analogous discussion
about dancing before the כלה. kallah. So because of that, that's what
made him so special and gave him that special and yes.
Is it in this context, isn't there a תוספות Tosfos that explains
breaking of the glass in order to simmer down the abandon, the
wild abandon?
Yeah, the yeah,
that might be. It's not it's not a תוספות Tosfos here, but
it might it could be you're right. Okay, so the verse says
like this. ואחא מרכיב לה אכתפיה, V'Acha markiv lah achatefeih,
רב אחא Rav Acha would have the כלה kallah ride on his
shoulders ומרקיד umerakeid and dance. So ואמרו ליה רבנן v'amru lei rabanan
so the rabbis said to him, אנן מהו למעבד הכי? anan mahu
l'mevad hachi?
Can we do that? Can we put the כלה kallah on our
shoulders? אמר להו Amar lehu he said to them, אי דמיא עליכו
ככשורא לחי. ei damya aleichu k'kashura l'chai. If she's
it's like a beam, you know, to me she's just like dead
weight, there's no sexual, you know, sort of like stimulation as a
result of this. So it's just so if she's like you dead
weight, לחי l'chai then go ahead. ואי לא לא. V'ei lo lo.
But if it will be a but if it'll lead to like,
you know, improper sexual thoughts and other types of, you know, sexual
energy, then of course it would be forbidden. All right, which is
very fascinating, you know, because because it makes it seem that it's
very subjective and this gets to a whole discussion. Yeah, but it
was on his shoulder. This gets to a whole discussion in the
ראשונים Rishonim like what types of things in terms of male-female interactions
are subjective as opposed to what types of things are like objective
in terms of concerns about things that will lead to הרהורים. hirhurim.
There's a famous story that I mean not famous, I heard it
a lot, so anyway it's famous to me, about how the students
of רב אהרן סולובייצ'יק Rav Ahron Soloveichik went to him and said,
Rebbe, are we allowed to go mixed swimming? So he said yes.
They said, what yes? Said but Rebbe what what about הרהורים? hirhurim?
Said, oh, if you have הרהורים hirhurim it's אסור. assur.
So there you go. Same answer as this גמרא. Gemara. All right.
Yes, so just
point out that like you know you're not necessarily looking at the
woman, but you know but you're praising her for her eyes or
her grace. So clearly looking at her.
Yeah, you don't stare at her. Yeah, you looked at her picture.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So that's the next
line in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי
יונתן, Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, מותר להסתכל בפני
כלה כל שבעה. mutar l'histakel bifnei kallah kol shiva.
You could be looking at the כלה kallah the whole week, like
you know clearly like admiringly looking at her so that the husband
will say ooh all these guys are looking at her she's she's
really attractive, you know. כדי לחבבה על בעלה kedei l'chabevah al baalah
to make her dear to her husband. אבל לית הלכתא כוותיה Aval
leit hilchata kevataih we don't say that. That's just asking for trouble.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. מעבירין את המת Maavirin et hamet
so now that we did מרקדין בפני הכלה merakdin bifnei hakallah we
do with other forms of sort of community communities' participation right because
this is also like the community being משמח חתן וכלה mesameach chosson
v'kallah which is a very important idea right that's what all this
part of. So there's other elements where there are things that are
about you know that are not private affairs that ultimately they're things
I mean obviously they're people that are the primary participants of it
but then the idea that the whole community is supposed to turn
out to show its type of the way that this is a
celebrating or mourning as we're going to say by a מת met
these things publicly as well and communally as well. So we're going
to it's always very interesting parallels between the חתונה chasunah and you
know and burial and שבעה shivah and so on. So meaning already
you know there's obvious comparisons about the whole idea of שבעה shivah
and שלושים shloshim and those types of things. But the point also
is is that there's also you know to acknowledge the communal element,
right? There's a week of שבע ברכות sheva brachot where the community
participates and says שבע ברכות sheva brachot or whatever and there's a
week of the community is מנחם menachem doing שבעה. shivah. There is
משמח בפני חתן וכלה mesameach bifnei chosson v'kallah and there is you
know the idea about like being מלווה melaveh and מספיד maspid you
know the מת. met. So there's an aspect about how these are
very much communal experiences and communal participation. So תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
so our rabbis taught. מעבירין את המת מלפני הכלה. Maavirin et hamet
milifnei hakallah.
Here you are, you have these two huge groups of people of
you know you've got one sort of company of people going out
and leading the כלה kallah to the wedding hall or whatever it
is and you've got this other group that's leading a coffin out
to the funeral and they're bumping into each other in the middle
of the street. So who gets the right of way? So the
הלכה halacha is the כלה kallah gets the right of way which
is a you know profound like if you were a קהלת Kohelet
person you would say טוב ללכת אל בית אבל מללכת אל בית
משתה
tov lalechet el beit avel milalechet el
beit
mishteh right והחי יתן אל לבו. v'hachai yiten el libo. But it's
interesting that the rabbis then make a much more life affirming type
of a statement and the sort of and you know and showing
שמחה simcha to the you know and sort of also like attending
to the living and the joy of the living and supporting those
that are you know you know the joy of the next generation
in a way which is also suggested by the חתן וכלה chosson
v'kallah that takes precedence over the over the dead.
But nevertheless, I was told still and I think it's actually the
הלכה halacha I mean you can let me know if that's not
the case that like you know if you have to If you
have the option of going to be the tenth man at like
a שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos or a tenth man at שבעה Shiva
מנין minyan you should still go to the שבעה Shiva
מנין. minyan. Fantastic.
I don't know, I had that exact question.
Really? Really?
That's an interesting question.
Well, it could just be because of that one is more of
a חיוב chiyuv for the אבל avel to be. I mean, it's
an interesting question.
I can see the logic for that but I have to, I
can't say that definitively. Okay, let's see.
This is the מת met goes first. No, מעבירין את המת.
ma'avirin et hamet.
You pass the מת met aside in order to give, in order
to make way for the כלה. kallah. מפני כלה. mipnei kallah. וזה
וזה, vezah vezah, and both of those companies will step aside מפני
מלך ישראל mipnei melech Yisrael from the, for the king. King always
comes first. אמרו עליו על אגריפס המלך שעבר מפני הכלה. amru alav
al Agrippas hamelech she-avar mipnei hakallah. So אגריפס המלך Agrippas hamelech was
so, seems to have done this wonderful thing and he stepped aside
in order to make way for a כלה kallah for a wedding
party.
ושבחו חכמים. veshibchu chachamim. And the sages praised him. Look, he's מוחל
על כבודו. mochel al kvodo. So the גמרא Gemara says, שבחו, shibchu,
they praised him, מכלל דשפיר עביד. michal de-shapir avid. You're saying he
did something good? ואמר רב אשי, ve-amar Rav Ashi, אפילו מאן דאמר
נשיא שמחל על כבודו כבודו מחול. afilu man de-amar nasi she-machal al
kvodo, kvodo machul. Even if you say that a נשיא nasi like
a prince, you know, a governor can be מוחל mochel on his
כבוד, kvod, but מלך שמחל על כבודו, melech she-machal al kvodo, a
king who tries to, you know, be מוחל mochel on his כבודו,
kvodo, אין כבודו מחול. ein kvodo machul. He is not in a,
he is not able to waive his honor. דאמר מר, de-amar mar,
because we say, שום תשים עליך מלך. som tasim alecha melech. You
shall place a king upon you. The double of שום תשים som
tasim that he, his authority has to always be over you. שתהא
אימתו עליך. she-tehei emato alecha. That the, you need to have the
power of the authority of the, you know, office of the king.
So he's not allowed to waive his honor. Someone tied it into
the fact that, you know, that it's also, I think the מהרש"א
Maharsha says, חלק מכבודו לבשר ודם, chalak michvodo le-basar ve-dam, that the
king also is some type of a model of divine kingship and
represents that idea. So there always has to be an element of
authority in terms of the king. So how was he allowed to
step aside? So the גמרא Gemara says, פרשת דרכים הוי. parashat drachim
havai. No, it was a crossroads, which means they weren't obviously stepping
aside. They bumped into each other in a crossroads and then the
king's party decided oh we have to make a left turn rather,
you know, and by making a left turn they made room for
the other party to go through. But it wasn't an obvious we're
going to step aside and let them pass. Okay, so it was
not so much of an obvious מחילה mechilah on their כבוד. kvod.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So now that we've sort of dealt between,
you know, that חתן chatan כלה kallah
precedes מת met and we've also dealt with this comparison of marriage
and תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, now we're going to look at תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah and burial and חתן chatan and כלה. kallah. So
let's take a look. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan.
מבטלין תלמוד תורה להוצאת המת ולהכנסת כלה. mevatlin Talmud Torah le-hotza'at hamet
ule-hachnasat kallah. You set aside, you, you know, תורה Torah learning, it's
sort of like the similar מעבירין ma'avirin for the sake of taking
out a dead body and for the sake of שמחת חתן וכלה.
simchas chatan ve-kallah. So you leave the בית מדרש Beis Medrash in
order to go be at a wedding. So אמרו עליו על רבי
יהודה בר אלעאי. amru alav al Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai. They said
about רבי יהודה בר אלעאי Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai שהיה מבטל תלמוד
תורה להוצאת המת ולהכנסת כלה. she-hayah mevatel Talmud Torah le-hotza'at hamet ule-hachnasat
kallah. He would leave the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. The same רבי
יהודה בר אלעאי Rabbi Yehuda bar Ilai you might remember that we
had before that took the הדס hadas and was מרקד merakked it.
So he was very much, it's very consistent. He was very, and
he was מוחל mochel on his כבוד התורה. kevod ha-Torah. So here
he's actually being מוחל mochel on his תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah in
order to actually, you know, rejoice with people and their שמחות. simchas.
Okay, which is also again a profound type of, of a point
in terms of, you know, sort of how much is the rabbi
separating himself off from the community and I'm doing the most important
thing in the world and I'm learning תורה Torah and so on
and what I'm, and that also leads to and I'm better than
everybody else, right? It's almost like it almost evokes the whole,
what's his name, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai coming
out from the cave, right? But didn't he see also the guy
running with the two branches of הדס? hadas? לכבוד שבת. lichvod Shabbat.
Was it הדס hadas though? I think it was הדס. hadas. That
just occurred to me now. But anyway, you know, and being able
to appreciate like, you know, it's not all about you and your,
you and your super high level of תורה, Torah, you know, it's
also about people and their, and their general sort of שמחה simcha
and שמחה של מצווה simcha shel mitzvah and the, you know, and
so on. So there's something very powerful here. I mean sure, you
know, we could formalize it as a הלכה halacha principle that, you
know, תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah you say עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה
osek be-mitzvah patur min ha-mitzvah by תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah or not?
Well, if it's a מצווה mitzvah that somebody else can't do and
you're needed to do it or whatever, and the תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah can always be done later, you know, so you go ahead
and you, you know, מבטל mevatel etc. But I think that that
loses some of the power here about the idea of the, you
know, sort of symbolic or religious significance of leaving this high level
of תורה Torah learning and connecting to people, you know, at this
very sort of, you know, profound and, you know, real level way.
You know, and some explain that the whole reason that you leave
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah in order to do a מצווה mitzvah is
because like the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that, that I forget the exact
line of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi here, these two, but in general it's
a principle is because you're, you're, you know, you're supposed to be
לומד על מנת לעשות. lomed al menat la-asot. So כל הלומד שלא
על מנת לעשות מוטב לו שלא למד. kol ha-lomed she-lo al menat
la-asot, mutav lo she-lo lamad. Which basically is in a way does
somewhat capture that principle that learning
תורה. Torah. it also has to translate into the real world and
into how you actually are with people and there and what's meaningful
for them. Okay, so מבטלין תלמוד תורה להוצאת המת ולהכנסת כלה. mevatlin
talmud torah lehota’at hamet ulehachnasat kallah. אמרו עליו על רבי יהודה ברבי
אלעאי, amru alav al rabbi yehudah berabbi ilai, they said about רבי
יהודה ברבי אלעאי Rabbi Yehuda berabbi Ilai שהיה מבטל תלמוד תורה להוצאת
המת ולהכנסת כלה. shehayah mevatel talmud torah lehota’at hamet ulehachnasat kallah. במה
דברים אמורים, bamah devarim amurim, but now but now there's a step
back. When is this true? בשאין
עמו כל צרכו, beshein imo kol tzorko, when there are not enough
people to be part of the wedding party or part of the
burial. We're actually going to focus on the burial. אבל יש עמו
כל צרכו, aval yesh imo kol tzorko, if there are enough people,
then אין מבטלין, ein mevatlin, then you're not. So it's always like
striking a balance. Do we really need you to come? If you're
not really needed to be there, then stay in the בית מדרש.
bet midrash. וכמה כל צרכו, vechamah kol tzorko, what's considered enough? Of
course our definition of enough is going to be so crazy that
it's almost always going to need more people. אמר רבי שמואל בר
איני משמיה דרב, amar rabbi shmuel bar ini mishmeih derav, תריסר אלפי
גברי. treisar alfei gavrei. Well, if there's 12,000 people, then we've got
enough. ושיתא אלפי שיפורי veshita alfei shipurei and 6,000 shofars, which רש"י
Rashi said would call people to come but also just might be
part of like the whole procession. ואמרי לה תליסר אלפי גברי, veamrei
lah tlisar alfei gavrei, oh, 13,000 ומיניהו umineihu and from them שיתא
אלפי שיפורי, shita alfei shipurei, 6,000. So we're only talking about 13,000
people, not 18,000 people. That makes it more manageable. עולא אמר, ulla
amar, כגון דחייצי גברי מאבולא ועד סיכרא. kegon dechaitzei gavrei meabula vead
sichra. So maybe a more reasonable measure but still it's very high
high, that there are so many people they make a wall essentially
from the gate of the city all the way to the all
the way to the בית קברות, bet kvarot, all the way to
the cemetery. רב ששת ואיתימא רבי יוחנן אמר, rav sheshet veitima rabbi
yochanan amar, נטילתה כנתינתה. netilatah kentinatah. No, the removing of the Torah
is like the giving of the Torah. מה נתינתה בששים ריבוא, mah
nentinatah beshishim ribo, the same way it was given with 600,000 people,
אף נטילתה בששים ריבוא af netilatah beshishim ribo when it's taken away,
it's 600,000. So now we're clearly talking, which was not at all
clear before, about the death of a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. So
a death of a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, then there aren't enough
until 600,000, which also, by the way, points to the idea that
it's not just about the כבוד kvod of a מת met and
goes against what I was just saying before of חסד chesed and
the כלה, kallah, this is really about כבוד התורה. kvod hatorah. So
if it's כבוד התורה, kvod hatorah, so you leave your בית מדרש
bet midrash in order to show כבוד התורה. kvod hatorah. That's already
less of an interesting type of a trade-off, you know, because it's
about כבוד התורה. kvod hatorah.
Then why are we מבטל mevatel for the מת met and the
כלה kallah then?
I don't know, it's a good question. I mean, yeah, I mean
you'd say, would it be the same if it were a מת
met that was of this of this stature? I don't know. והני
מילי למאן דקרי ותני. vehanie milei leman dekari vetani. When is it
true that you need 600,000 if somebody learned פסוקים psukim that's קרי
kari and תני tani and he learned משניות mishnayot but he never
taught. אבל למאן דמתני, aval leman dematni, if somebody got to the
level of teaching Torah, לית ליה שיעורא, leit lei shiura, there's no
limit and anybody, and therefore everybody has to turn out even if
you already have 600,000 people. I mean you ever see the pictures
about, you know, the funeral about רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein
or about, you know, the לובביצר רבי Lubavitcher Rebbe or whatever. I
mean there were millions of people there.
עובדיה's Ovadia funeral I think probably was even larger than רב עובדיה.
Rav Ovadia. Right, רב עובדיה, Rav Ovadia, you know, of course according
to the גמרא, Gemara, all you have to do is be a
רבי rebbe and you're supposed to, it doesn't even have to be
a גדול הדור gadol hador in order to get that many people.
Anyway, so רש"י Rashi interestingly says לית ליה שיעורא leit lei shiura
וממילא umimeila רש"י Rashi says שמעינן דלמאן דלא קרי ולא תני, shmeinan
delman dela kari vela tani, let's say somebody isn't part of the
Torah world at all, אין מבטלין ein mevatlin אם יש לו מתעסקים
כדי
קבורה בעלמא. im yesh lo mitaskim kedei kvurah bealma. Then you just
have a very pragmatic type of a measure. Look, are there enough
people there that can actually get done what needs to get done?
Yes. So I don't need to be there just to make a
bigger deal about it. So then there's just like this huge gap
between the people, right? For a normal person, all right, if they
got 10 people there, they can say קדיש, Kaddish, they got enough
people to dig the grave, fine. They don't need anybody more. But
if all of a sudden if it's a guy that learned פסוקים
psukim and משנה mishnah even if he never taught, then we're going
to need 13,000
people, and if they're less than that then I'm going to turn
out. So it really does become much more of an issue of
כבוד התורה kvod hatorah makes you leave the בית מדרש bet midrash
than like כבוד המת. kvod hamet. You know, it is interesting. Michael,
talk sometimes, you do get these practical questions. There's going to be
a funeral, graveside thing, nobody, a person died, has like no family
or friends or whatever. Do we יחטוף מנין yachtof minyan of guys
out of the בית מדרש bet midrash in order to go ahead
and let the family say קדיש? Kaddish? It's like a serious question,
taking people, 10 people for six hours out of the בית מדרש
bet midrash or whatever. So I mean those are real questions. And
but it is again fascinating that by the case like of הכלה,
hakallah, you don't sort of say like, oh, he's got to be
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham or something like that or whatever. I
mean there it's not about כבוד התורה, kvod hatorah, but here all
of a sudden, you know, there it's about you leave Torah in
order to be משמח חתן וכלה mesameach chatan vekallah like in the
whole story about the רב יהודה ברבי אלעאי, Rabbi Yehudah berabbi Ilai,
but all of a sudden by the מת met it shifted to
this whole issue about being about כבוד התורה. kvod hatorah. So that
was an interesting shift. Yes.
And this must be criteria of some sort of personal relationship, right?
We're talking only in the abstract when we go to the wedding,
when you're invited.
Right, when you're invited, right. Well, that also leads to, I mean
we were discussing that last night, an idea that if you're invited
to, if you're invited to a סעודת מצוה seudat mitzvah you have
to go, or funeral. Or funeral. funeral. Right, so you're not invited,
you're informed. You're informed. You should know the ברית bris is taking
place on this date or whatever, it'd be lovely if you were
there, we're not inviting you.
Maybe there was no such concept as an invitation to a wedding.
Because the whole village showed up. The village showed up. Well, it
could be that everybody was in the village. I'm not saying, but
in other words, it was a whole concept.
Yeah. Okay, good point. All right, back now, continuing on to more
wedding practices but here with a הלכה Halacha perspective. אי יש עדים
שיצאה בהינומא, ei yesh edim sheyatzah behinuma,
if there were witnesses that she went out בהינומא, behinuma, then you
know that it was a first wedding. מאי הינומא? mai hinuma? What's
this הינומא? hinuma? So סורחב בר פפא, Surhav bar Pappa, I know
סורחב בר פפא Surhav bar Pappa from the סיום Siyum line. סורחב
בר פפא, דורא בר פפא, רפא בר פפא. Surhav bar Pappa, Dora
bar Pappa, Rafa bar Pappa. Okay, סורחב בר פפא משמיה דזירי, Surhav
bar Pappa mishmei d'Ziri, when you do the דף יומי Daf Yomi
you say that line a lot. סורחב בר פפא משמיה דזירי אמר,
Surhav bar Pappa mishmei d'Ziri amar, תנורא דאסא, tanura d'asa,
literally an oven of myrtle, but really רש"י Rashi says it sort
of means like a dome. Like you make like a dome of
myrtle, sort of like maybe as a חופה chuppah or something. No,
I thought רש"י Rashi sort of meant more like a חופה, chuppah,
more like for them to walk under.
Sounds like, you know, thinking of like these wreaths that you
know that they used to wear. No, I thought it meant like,
you know, like whatever, yeah, like a dome to walk under or
something. Anyway, ורבי יוחנן אמר, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar, קביסתא דמנמנו בה כלתא,
kviyasta d'mnamnu bah kalsah,
a type of a cover that the כלתא kallah dozes off in.
רש"י Rashi says that it's some type of a veil or some
type of thing that covers her eyes. So as long as it's
covering her eyes, she could close her eyes for a little bit
and get a little catnap, especially if the wedding's schlepping on late.
Okay, so some type... it's interesting. I mean, you know, if it
seems like some type of a parallel either to the veil or
to the חופה, chuppah, which are obviously things that we still have
in one form or another. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka omer. Now רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka
says the
giving off of the, you know, roasted grain is enough of an
evidence. So תנא ביהודה ראיה, Tanna: B'Yehuda ra'aya, so a ברייתא Braitisa
says this is a proof in יהודה Yehuda that that's what they
would do, they would give off roasted grain. But בבבל מאי? B'Bavel
mai? So now the גמרא Gemara is asking, how about in Babylonia?
What are our practices that would be evident that it was a
first wedding? So אמר רב דרדוגי דמשחא ארישא דרבנן, amar Rav: dardugei
d'mishcha areisha d'rabbanan, dripping of oil on the head of the rabbis.
So apparently here again you get rabbis again, again, all this intersection
of תורה Torah and weddings. So presumably, you know, it would maybe,
you know, you want to be blessing the חתן chosson and כלה
kallah with תורה Torah or something. Whatever you do, any of the
rabbis, if you go to the rabbis' table, I gotta tell you,
if you've been a rabbi like and they put you at the
rabbis' table at a wedding, it's like a death knell. Anyway, it's
like I don't want to be at the rabbis' table, it's no
fun there, everybody's got to all be important and not... anyway, okay.
So, everyone's worried about how the other rabbi's looking at him. Anyway,
so they go over to the rabbis' table with a bottle of
oil and they pour head on the oil of the rabbis and
that's what they would do at a first wedding. Okay, so אמרי
ליה רב פפא לאביי, amrei lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye, so רב פפא
Rav Pappa said to אביי: Abaye: isn't that like the Gatorade? Okay,
right. משחא דחפיפותא קאמר מר, mishcha d'chafifusa kama mar, so are you
saying that you would actually take like oil for rubbing on your
head? Meaning, it's not, you know, רש"י Rashi sort of says, are
you basically saying that, you know, that they need like, you know,
that they need to be, like that they're smelly or that they
need oil on them? Something like offended him that made him feel
that this was not appropriate. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said
back to him, יתמא, yatma, orphan, right, which is interesting because אביי
Abaye was orphaned. And רב פפא Rav Pappa saying... אביי Abaye is
responding to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, but maybe he means that, he
means, you know, you're not an orphan, you know, לא עבדה lo
avda or it seems like you are, ולא עבדה לך אמך דרדוגי
משחא ארישא דרבנן בשעת מעשה, v'lo avda lach immach dardugei mishcha areisha
d'rabbanan b'sha'as ma'aseh, when you got married, you're telling me that your
mother didn't go ahead and do this and do this ritual of
pouring oil on the tops of the, you know, of the rabbis?
So it is again very poignant that he calls him orphan, meaning
you're acting like you didn't have a mother who did this for
you when you got married that you're taking offense at this. And
of course אביי Abaye himself was, you know, was an orphan. Okay.
כי הא דהוא מרבנן, ki hada d'hu merabbanan, like the story about
one of those rabbis דאסיק ליה לבריה, d'isik lei l'brei, he married
off his son בי רבה בר רב עולא bei Rabbah bar Rav
Ulla to the house of רבה בר רב עולא, Rabbah bar Rav
Ulla, meaning to a daughter of רבה בר רב עולא, Rabbah bar
Rav Ulla, ואמרי לה רבה בר עולא אסיק ליה לבריה בי ההוא
מרבנן, v'amrei lei Rabbah bar Ulla asik lei l'brei bei hahu merabbanan,
or the opposite, רבה בר רב עולא Rabbah bar Rav Ulla married
his son off into the house, to the daughter of one of
these rabbis, ודרדיג משחא
ארישא דרבנן בשעת מעשה,
v'dardig
mishcha
areisha d'rabbanan b'sha'as ma'aseh, and they poured
dripped oil over on the heads of the rabbis at the time
of the wedding. Now אלמנותא מאי, almanusa mai, what do we do
for an אלמנה? almana? Right, because if you remember before, the גמרא
Gemara about the barrel of wine that they wanted some type of
a not just an absence of a practice, but some type of
a concrete practice that they would do for second wedding. But the
גמרא... Gemara... so the גמרא Gemara does not give that answer, the
גמרא Gemara says, so תני רב יוסף אלמנותא ליתא כיסני, tani Rav
Yosef: almanusa leisa kisnai, by an אלמנה almana they don't hand out
the parched, the what is it, parched, grilled, whatever, roasted, thank you,
roasted grain. So תוספות Tosafot says, alright, what was the answer, like
it sounded like you wanted something Okay, ומודי רבי יהושע באומר לחבירו.
u-modeh Rabbi Yehoshua be-omer le-chavero. So that was a lot of fun
about getting an insight into weddings, and now we get back to
the discussion about the מיגו. migo. So Rabbi Yehuda agrees, like Rabbi
Yehoshua says, even though I basically reject מיגו, migo, I concede הפה
שאסר. ha-peh she-asar. So a guy comes and says, "This field that
I'm on, I got it from your father and I purchased it
from him." Once it belonged to your father, he's believed because he
didn't have to say anything. And I'll remind you it's a debate
of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. רש"י Rashi says it means that
the other person whose father apparently originally owned the field didn't say
anything, he just he was completely oblivious. And that's why Rabbi Yehoshua
concedes that you said something, you could have been completely silent, the
other guy was oblivious, then you're totally believed. תוספות Tosafot says a
little bit more of a חידוש chiddush that no, the other guy
does say, "Hey, what are you doing on that field? That field
was my father's." Okay, but there's no evidence that needs answering. Okay,
it's just סתם קלא. stam kala. So he could have, he didn't,
he could be silent, but he could have said לא היו דברים
מעולם, lo hayu devarim me-olam, it's completely false. And so when he
concedes the point that, "Yes, I admit it was your father's, but
I purchased it," then he has a הפה שאסר. ha-peh she-asar. That's
already more of a חידוש. chiddush. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. ורמינהי ומודי רבי יהושע באומר לחבירו, U-remi-ne-hi u-modeh
Rabbi Yehoshua be-omer le-chavero, שדה זו של אביך היתה ולקחתיה ממנו. sadeh
zu shel avicha hayetah u-lekachtiha mimenu. Why doesn't he say that, why
does he say "the father"? Why doesn't he say even if he
concedes that it was yours originally and I purchased it from you?
Now, according to רש"י, Rashi, that's a more of a bizarre suggestion,
like how could this guy be oblivious that it was once his,
you know? So according to תוספות, Tosafot, though, תוספות Tosafot says no,
why don't you have it that the guy says, "What are you
doing on my field?" He doesn't have any evidence, but he's saying
it's my field. Yes, it's your field, but I purchased it from
you. That's so that's a good question. That's a stronger case because,
as תוספות Tosafot points out, it's ברי וברי. bari u-bari. The guy
doesn't just come and say it's my father's and maybe he only
knows secondhand or whatever. He's saying, "It's my field." And nevertheless, Rabbi
Yehoshua says since there's no evidence that needs answering, you're believed to
say I purchased it from you. Okay, so why didn't you say
the guy says it's my field? So the גמרא Gemara says משום
דקבעי למיתני סיפא, mishum de-ka-ba'ei le-mitni seifa, אם יש עדים שהיא שלו
והוא אומר לקחתיה הימנו אינו נאמן. im yesh edim she-hi shelo ve-hu
omer lekachtiha heimenu eino ne'eman. If there are witnesses that originally belonged
to the other guy, then he's not believed to say he got
it from him. So the גמרא Gemara says look, that's pretty obvious.
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case in that second case? אי
דאכל שני חזקה, Ei de-achal shenei chazakah, if he ate the years
of חזקה, chazakah, שני shenei does not mean two, it means שנים
של. shanim shel. If he was there for three years, which establishes
חזקה, chazakah, so even though it originally belonged to another person, if
you're there for three years uncontested, it's evidence that it's yours. So
אמאי לא מהימן? amai lo meheiman? Even if there are witnesses it
was originally ראובן's, Reuven why wouldn't שמעון Shimon be believed? He's been
there for three years. And everyone knows it, and everyone knows it,
there are witnesses. אי דלא אכל שני חזקה, Ei de-lo achal shenei
chazakah, and if he didn't have three years of residence, פשיטא דלא
מהימן, peshita de-lo meheiman, of course he's not believed. I mean, what's
the חידוש chiddush at the end of the משנה mishnah that if
the guy has witnesses, if ראובן Reuven has witnesses, then שמעון Shimon
isn't believed? Of course not. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי לא
אכל פשיטא דלא מהימן. ve-i lo achal peshita de-lo meheiman. So therefore,
we had to say a case of the father, so that makes
it more understandable, that makes it more of a חידוש. chiddush. The
גמרא Gemara says how does introducing the father help? אי הכי גבי
אביו נמי, I hachi gabei aviv nami, how does it introducing the
father into this make it any different? אי דאכל שני חזקה אמאי
לא מהימן, Ei de-achal shenei chazakah amai lo meheiman, if שמעון Shimon
was there for three years, why isn't he believed? ואי דלא אכל
שני חזקה פשיטא. Ve-ei de-lo achal shenei chazakah peshita. And again, if
he wasn't there for three years, it's all obvious. So how does
introducing the father make the end of it any more understandable? פשיטא
דלא מהימן. Peshita de-lo meheiman. So the גמרא Gemara says no. בשלמא
גבי אביו, Bishlama gabei aviv, I can explain to you a case
by the father where there's a חידוש chiddush in the סיפא. seifa.
What's the case of the father? משכחת לה דאכל שתים בחיי האב
ואחת בחיי בנו. Mashkachat lah de-achal shtayim be-chayei ha-av ve-achat be-chayei beno.
That you have been on this field for three years of residence,
two years was when שמעון's Shimon father was alive, and one year
now that שמעון Shimon is alive. Okay, so you might think, look,
I've got three years, I should win. And the answer is you
don't. Since שמעון Shimon has proof that it was originally his, your
three years do not entitle you to it. Why not? I've been
on it three years. Because three years which is not all the
same person, two the father, one the son, doesn't count as the
three years as we're going to see. So וכדרב הונא, u-che-de-Rav Huna,
like רב הונא Rav Huna teaches, דאמר רב הונא, d'amar Rav Huna,
אין מחזיקין בנכסי קטן, ein machzikin be-nichsei katan, you do not, you
cannot claim possession of the property of a minor, אפילו הגדיל, afilu
higdil, even if he becomes an adult. So meaning that the case
is not, I mean, although תוספות Tosafot discusses this, but we'll take
the גמרא Gemara literally, is not that שמעון Shimon was an adult
when you started being on the field. What happened was you started
on the field and שמעון Shimon was a minor and you were
eating it for the father's field, the father's field, you were eating
it on it for two years, the father was alive, the father
was an adult, שמעון Shimon was a minor, and then the father
dies, and then you continue eating on it for a third year
and שמעון Shimon remains, is still a minor. So that's why you're
not believed, because שמעון Shimon is a minor. A minor is not
supposed presumably able to be aware who's on his field and that
he should protest if you don't belong. belong to him too long
and short. Now that you could say is pretty much of an
obvious חידוש. chiddush. The bigger חידוש chiddush is אפילו הגדיל, afilu higdil,
that now you've been on that field for ten years, but the
first year was before שמעון'ס Shimon's בר מצווה. bar mitzvah. So the
point is even the other nine years don't count, because once your
initial relationship to that was at a time when שמעון Shimon was
not seen as being responsible and aware of what was going on
to register it, then the fact that you continue to be on
it when he was an adult, he just put that in the
original context of when you were there the year before when he
wasn't responsible for understanding what your presence was about. You have to
leave and come back. Yeah, or something, or you have to get
a שטר shtar is what you have to get. So anyway, okay,
so that's the חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that in the
סיפא seifa you're not believed even if you have years of חזקה,
chazakah, since since we're talking about a father and a child, we
can frame it that those years of חזקה chazakah began in the
life of the child as as an underaged person, and that's why
your years of חזקה chazakah don't help you. Okay, כגון דאמר רב
הונא אין מחזיקין בנכסי קטן אפילו הגדיל. kegon d'amar Rav Huna ein
machzikin b'nichsei katan afilu higdil. So רב הונא מתניתין אתא לאשמעינן? Rav
Huna matnitin ata l'ashmeinan? If that's פשט pshat in our משנה, mishna,
who needs רב הונא? Rav Huna? רב הונא Rav Huna is coming
to tell us our משנה? mishna? So the answer is it's not
so obvious in the משנה. mishna. אי בעית אימא רב הונא דיוקא
דמתניתין קאמר. ei bayit eima Rav Huna diyuka d'matnitin ka'amar. Number one
is just because our משנה mishna says you're not believed, the משנה's
mishna not saying anything at all about, you know, about beginning when
the kid was a minor and continuing and blah blah blah. So
that's how רב הונא Rav Huna is explaining our משנה, mishna, you
know, or actually רב הונא Rav Huna didn't explain the משנה mishna
but we used רב הונא Rav Huna to explain the משנה. mishna.
That you're not believed if שמעון Shimon has evidence, because even though
you have years of חזקה, chazakah, they started, some of them started
while שמעון Shimon was still a minor. ואי בעית אימא v'ei bayit
eima if I want I could tell you אפילו הגדיל קמשמע לן,
afilu higdil k'mashma lan, that the חידוש chiddush of רב הונא Rav
Huna is is that it's not only does years when שמעון Shimon
is a minor don't count, but if it started when שמעון Shimon
was a minor then it doesn't then your חזקה chazakah doesn't count
even as שמעון Shimon gets to be an adult. לתני בדידיה ולוקמה
כגון שאכל שתיים בפניו ואחת שלא בפניו, litnei b'didei v'lokmah kegon she'achal
shtayim befanav v'achat shelo befanav, so the גמרא Gemara says I still
don't get why we had to be talking about the father. Why
not talk about the person, and I'll give you another scenario where
your חזקה chazakah won't count. What would be the case? That you
had חזקה, chazakah, but the guy wasn't around. He was in the
neighboring village. Now the whole reason that חזקה chazakah works, this is
I was sort of implicitly saying this by the case of the
קטן, katan, but let me spell it out. The reason that residency
works is by by field it's all supposed to be about a
שטר. shtar. It's all supposed to be about because you can't take
physical possession and walk away with it. So it's all supposed to
have to be like, you know, whenever you buy real estate you
got to register it in like the what is it? the county
or somewhere anyway, you see, you know, the courts there needs to
be like a registry. So your שטר shtar is basically your registry.
So if you don't have a שטר shtar you should automatically lose.
Okay, except that we say that if you're on there three years
uncontested like the IRS you don't have to save receipts after three
years, right? Seven? Seven now? Okay, anyway, if it's oops well because
you know why because we digitized it all now so it's anyway,
if it's and put it all in the cloud and then everybody
can have it. Anyway if it's three years and it's uncontested you're
not responsible to hold onto the שטר. shtar. But the key is
it's uncontested. If it's contested you should be holding onto it. So
you have to interpret the lack of being contested as now I
don't have to worry about it if anybody wanted to make a
claim they would have made it against me by not making a
claim they're implicitly saying just you know waiving their rights etc. So
all of that is only meaningful if the other person could contest
it. So he has to be around. He has to be around
to hear that you're on the field, although that is assumed to
be that that message will get to him even in the neighboring
village although we're going to discuss it that that message will get
to him because people will say hey you know ראובן'ס Reuven's on
that field of yours. Okay, people are going to tell about it,
but he also has to be be able to if he says
I protest, that that message will get all the way back to
ראובן Reuven and that's less likely that that'll travel in that direction.
What? Less likely? Oh, more likely that you'd make sure. You're going
to send the letter, that's true, but the גמרא Gemara wasn't dealing
with letters, it was just you protested in front of people in
front of you and somehow the news travels. Anyway, so it has
to be in a context where the message goes in both directions.
Okay, so a case where it wouldn't be חזקה chazakah might be
a case of שלא בפניו. shelo befanav. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. לתני בדידיה ולוקמה כגון שאכל שתיים בפניו ואחת שלא בפניו.
litnei b'didei v'lokmah kegon she'achal shtayim befanav v'achat shelo befanav. This is
what we're trying to answer. What are we trying to answer? We're
trying to answer why the משנה mishna had the case about I
bought it from your father. Tell me a bigger חידוש, chiddush, even
if he says yes I admit I bought it from you. He
says no, bought it from the father to explain the end of
the משנה mishna where it says that if there was evidence that
it was the other guy's field you're not believed. So the גמרא
Gemara says of course you're not believed. So no, it's a חידוש
chiddush that you're not believed even though you have חזקה. chazakah. Why
are you not believed even though you have חזקה? chazakah? Because it
was a case of father and son and da-da-da and therefore father
and son the חזקה chazakah isn't meaningful so we set it up
with father to say that you wouldn't be believed in certain scenarios
even with a חזקה. chazakah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says I
can set up the scenario where you're not believed with a חזקה
chazakah even with the guy himself if it was not in his
presence. Okay, לתני בדידיה ולוקמה כגון שאכל שתיים בפניו ואחת שלא בפניו,
litnei b'didei v'lokmah kegon she'achal shtayim befanav v'achat shelo befanav, one of
the years was not in the guy's presence. אכל achal because part
of the idea of residence on the field is that you're working
the field and eating its produce. וכגון שברח, u'chegon shebarach, so and
like the owner ran away and he can't and he's. And he
can’t come back. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ברח מחמת מאי?
barach machmat mai? What would be the scenario that he ran away?
אי דברח מחמת נפשות, Ei d’barach machmat nefashot, if he ran away
because he’s fearful for his life, פשיטא דלא מהני. pishita d’lo mehani.
So then you wouldn't need the משנה Mishnah to tell me that.
That would be obvious. Like guy isn't going to go ahead and
make a protest if he's hiding for his life because the government's
after him. דלא מצי מחי. D’lo matzi machi. And if he can't
protest. ואי דברח מחמת ממון, V’ei d’barach machmat mamon, and if he's
just hiding because he doesn't want creditors to find him, איבעי ליה
למחויי. ibai lei l’michuyei. Then he should protest, and it's not an
excuse not to protest, because here he's also protecting his financial interests.
דקיימא לן מחאה שלא בפניו הויא מחאה, D’kayma lan mecha’ah shelo b’fanav
havya mecha’ah, because a protest not in presence would have counted. And
therefore the lack of protest is meaningful. דתנן, D’tnan, we taught in
a משנה: Mishnah: שלש ארצות לחזקה. Shalosh aratzot l’chazakah. There are three
lands when it comes to taking possession: יהודה ועבר הירדן והגליל, Yehudah
v’Ever HaYarden v’haGalil, Judea, the Trans-Jordan, and the Galilee. היה ביהודה והחזיק
בגליל, Hayah b’Yehudah v’hechezik b’Galil, if the guy, the owner of the
field, was in יהודה Yehudah and the other person was in possession
of his property in the גליל, Galil, בגליל והחזיק ביהודה, B’Galil v’hechezik
b’Yehudah, the reverse, אינו חזקה, eino chazakah, it's not a good חזקה,
chazakah, עד שיהא עמו במדינה, ad sheyehei imo b’medinah, until you're in
the same country. והוינן בה, V’havinan ban, we asked on this: מאי
קסבר? Mai kasavar? What does he hold? אי קסבר מחאה שלא בפניו
הויא מחאה, Ei kasavar mecha’ah shelo b’fanav havya mecha’ah, that a protest
not in the guy's presence will be, will be heard? And since
it will be heard, the lack of protest is meaningful and therefore
חזקה chazakah is meaningful. So if מחאה mecha’ah works, that means חזקה
chazakah is meaningful. In that case, אפילו ביהודה וגליל נמי, afillu b’Yehudah
v’Galil nami, even in different countries we should say that news should
travel and you should be able to do a חזקה. chazakah. ואי
קסבר מחאה שלא בפניו לא הויא מחאה, V’ei kasavar mecha’ah shelo b’fanav
lo havya mecha’ah, and if not being in the presence will not,
your protest won't be heard and חזקה chazakah won't work, אפילו ביהודה
ויהודה נמי לא. afillu b’Yehudah v’Yehudah nami lo. So even in the
same country, as long as you're not in your presence in a
different city it should not be a good חזקה. chazakah. So what
is this state? What is the idea that countries matter? Either you
always have to be ממש, mamash, like in the same town, in
the same city, or even in a different country it won't matter.
But either way, if we're, now obviously the logical thing would be
to say news travels but only so far. Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara wants to understand what's your position? If news travels then you
should always work and if news doesn't travel it should not work
even in the same country. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר אבא
בר ממל, Amar Abba bar Memel, לעולם קסבר מחאה שלא בפניו הויא
מחאה. le’olam kasavar mecha’ah shelo b’fanav havya mecha’ah. Really, not in the
presence does work, news does travel. ומתניתין בשעת חירום שנויה, U’matnitin b’sha’at
cheirum shanoy, and our משנה Mishnah is at a time when there
is like a like there's an edict out that doesn't allow travel.
Okay, there's an emergency situation and you're not allowed to travel. And
that makes things different. ומה ישנא יהודה וגליל דנקט? U’mah shna Yehudah
v’Galil d’nakat? So why are we talking about יהודה Yehudah and גליל?
Galil? דסתם יהודה וגליל כשעת חירום דמו, D’stam Yehudah v’Galil k’sha’at cheirum
damu, because as a general rule, right, border crossings between יהודה Yehudah
and גליל Galil generally were very difficult. Okay, so basically what it's
saying is, which is probably what we would have intuited anyway, news
travels within a certain country's borders much more than it crosses a
borders, particularly if there's like political reasons why those border crossings don't
happen. Okay, so the bottom line though about the גמרא Gemara is,
is that yes you could have had a scenario where the משנה
Mishnah would have made sense that even your חזקה chazakah doesn't work
because it's a case of שלא בפניו. shelo b’fanav. And there are
cases that are שלא בפניו shelo b’fanav that חזקה chazakah doesn't work,
but that the גמרא Gemara would have said was less of a
חידוש chiddush than the case about the father and the son. So
that's why the whole משנה Mishnah is talking about a case of
a father to tell me that when there is proof that it's
the first guy's field, then you don't win even if you have
חזקה chazakah if it was one of this type of a scenario
about חזקה chazakah in the son's property when the son was a
minor. It's tough to move from one country to another city. Ah,
דוקא. dafka. Without the metro section. Aha. Right. World of distance.